How are we doing?
Nice to see you here.
It's a pleasure to be with you.
I'm a little nervous, I'm
telling you now so you know.
I would love for us to spend
some quality time together chatting.  I
don't know if what I have to tell you will
interest you,
but I'll try.
My name is Blanca Portillo,
I am also known
as Rojiblanca Portillo.
I have been with Atlético de Madrid
all my life.  I
declare myself addicted to acting.
It's what I love most in the world
and what I dedicate all my time,
energy and passion to.
I would love to share with you
how I got started in this
and why I love it the way I do.
First of all, it changed my life.
Secondly,
it is what has taught me the most
in all the experiences I have had.  It has
been my guide,
what has opened the doors to the world for me,
what has made me
know myself
and others better.
I am the fourth daughter of eight.
We are eight siblings
from a very normal family.
Rather pulling towards a low economy.
My father died
when I was 18 years old.
I studied vocational training
when I finished high school.
What used to be the EGB.
And I studied
professional administration training.
When I was 13 or 14 years old I
didn't really know
what I wanted to be in life, I
didn't have the slightest idea.
I loved the idea
of telling stories,
because I admit that I have been a reader
since I was very little.
Because, probably,
since I didn't like the life I had,
the best way to escape it
was by reading.  I
put myself inside a book
and lived that book, I
lived as the characters lived
and I was transported to other places,
to other worlds,
to other cities, to other paradises.
This allowed me to escape a reality that,
let me tell you, I didn't like very much.
After studying the training,
I decided
that if I wanted to tell stories
or contact people,
which I really liked too,
the best profession I could choose,
don't laugh,
was a conference hostess.
Why?  Well, I don't know.
I thought it was interesting to be with people, to
be able to share
and, if I had a conference, I would
surely learn things
and could, well,
grow in a certain way.
I started studying this.
I went to a few conferences
where I was bored to death.
They put a uniform on you and you just had to
say good afternoon, come by,
good afternoon, come by...
And that wasn't telling stories
or being with people.
But I was lucky
to have a teacher,
a teacher
who taught us Tourist Geography.
And he had a theater group.
I had no connection with the theater.
In my personal life...
My mother and grandmother
liked going to the theater and the cinema,
but I had only been there
once in my life.
No more.
I fell in love with that teacher.
Everything he explained was so fascinating, he
was so intelligent, so wonderful... It
was a very platonic love.
Sitting and listening to him
was like reading a book,
traveling to other places.
It opened your mind, made you analyze
things in a different way.
At that time, he was choosing people
to join his theater group,
who were somewhat select,
the group of the exquisite.  I did
n't get in the first year,
and in the second year he invited me
to participate in the theater group.
At that time,
I was very obsessed with Lorca.  I've
always liked him, since I was young,
and the whole story around him,
everything that happened to him.
This moment in Spanish history
fascinated me.
Such a wonderful poet that
we suddenly lost in such a strange way.
And he was making a play about Lorca,
curiously enough.
Then,
to be able to be in that group, I said:
“Let's be there.”
I had a boyfriend
who I was going to marry.  We
already had an apartment,
we had a lot of things
more or less done.
I was 18 years old, I was very young,
but I was very clear
that he was, in a way,
the man of my life
and that, on the other hand, there was
my profession or my career.
Then,
when we started doing theater,
I discovered a
completely strange world
that made me travel for real, not by reading.
The character was me
and the one experiencing things was me.
One day at a rehearsal,
someone who was watching this rehearsal
approached me and said,
“You really moved me.”
And that became the pinnacle,
thinking that the emotion
I felt while doing that work,
or that research,
because it wasn't even a job,
transcended my own being
and connected with another who was
in front of me and produced an emotion in him.
That was like saying:
"It can't be, this is magic.
In other words, what I feel,
someone outside can feel,
saying things and experiencing things,
not reading them."
From that moment on, I decided
that that was what I wanted to do.  It
combined the two things
that interested me most,
which was telling stories
and being with people,
because a large part of this work
is related to the idea of teamwork.
Interpretation does
not exist by itself,
you with yourself,
but there must be a receiver
and, then,
people with whom you share it.
I remember that I didn't know
that this was being studied.
Then, the boyfriend I had told me:
“Well, yes, there is a place called the
Real Escuela Superior
de Arte Dramático y Danza de Madrid”.
"And what is studied there?"
"Let's go see it."  I approached it.
At that time it was in the Plaza de Ópera,
where the Teatro Real is today.
I took some tests
where they asked you to
interpret a text in verse
and do an improvisation
and a written exam.  They took
me, I passed.
And then I started studying.
I didn't get on stage again
until I finished training.
When I finished it,
there was a very important man there
named José Luis Gómez,
who is one of our great actors,
directors and producers,
who called for auditions
for a play
when I was already in the third year, finishing.
The play was "Blood Weddings".
Life rhymed,
Lorca appeared in my life again.
I didn't want to take the tests
because I remember
being happy at school,
in that ideal placenta,
where we talked about theater all day
and created.
Going out and facing the profession
for me was a world
that terrified me a lot
because I didn't know how it worked.  I
remember my teacher,
Pepe Estruch, told me:
"Don't be afraid,
take this test
and, if you fail,
get out of here, because you have to get out,
at some point you have to leave the
place where you are being educated
and put into practice what you have learned."  I
showed up for the tests
almost at gunpoint,
because I didn't want to.
Mr. Gomez caught me.
Then,
this prevented me from doing the fourth year,
which was already just a set-up.
I gave up directing,
but that opened the doors
to professional theater for me.
Just finished, at 21 years old.  I
realized that
what I had learned,
I felt would be of no use to me.
Because you believe, while you're learning,
that what they teach you...
"What's that for?".
Then it turned out
that I could apply everything I had learned
to that job.
Gómez himself told me
that I had good training,
because I was aware
of my body in space,
I knew how to manage my emotions,
I put my voice in its place,
I was able to understand
what a character meant
within the structure of the performance.
I began to realize
that all those subjects
that I thought were not about theater,
that were about studying, were super useful.
So, well,
I joined that company
and went on tour.
Here was
another critical moment in my life
because I decided that getting married
and moving out...
made no sense.
That the world was immense,
that life was full of challenges,
full of places to discover,
people to share with
and what it meant to do my life.
If I stayed home
with my wonderful boyfriend, it
wouldn't work
because it was like incompatible,
in a way.
I wanted to keep running and walking.
So, in a way, this marks
a turning point in my existence
and, from there, I am
lucky to have
never stopped working for
more than six months in my life.
Think about it, that was 20 or 21 years ago
and I'm 55.
So, I just really appreciate
the push from my teacher, who said,
"Take the tests."
And to the guy who said:
“There is the School
of Dramatic Art and Dance,”
without knowing what he was doing.
Or that's kind of the origin
of why I dedicate myself to this.  I've
never stopped doing it
because it's always different,
because it has taught me a lot,
I learn a lot every day
from the people I work with,
from the people who sit in front
to watch a performance.  I have
known countries, ways of thinking, it has
opened my mind a lot, it has
taught me a lot
and it continues to do so every day.  That's
why I think I
never lose my desire for it
and it continues to give me
enormous excitement and a huge sense of vertigo.
Over the years, it scares me more and more.
So anyone who thinks that this
is disappearing over the years is
wrong.
The fear increases
because the more time you dedicate to it
and the more experience you have, the
more responsibility you have.
Before, you would make a character who would come out,
say "good afternoon" and leave.
Now, you have a 50-page monologue.
Therefore, the responsibility
is becoming greater and greater,
and the fear is increasing.  You
don't know what people expect from you,
sometimes too much is expected, it
creates enormous insecurity,
but, even so, it still makes me happy.  The
day I lose my fear, I will stop doing it,
because if it doesn't scare me, it
no longer interests me.
I will feel like I already know everything
and, if I know everything, I
don't deserve to work on this.
So, well,
this is a bit of an introduction.
From now on,
if you want to ask me
anything, I
will be happy to share.
This is a chat, huh?
We talk to each other.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Sandra.
I am an actress
and theater teacher at Cuarta Pared.
Well, at Cuarta
we also do extracurricular activities
in schools.  We
don't want the kids to
be Blanca Portillo or Robert de Niro,
but, well, we do it because we believe it
's important for them
and that it's very good for them to relate.
My question is,
from your experience,
what benefits do you think theater has
on the children of our country?
Ugh, a lot, I'm sure.
In fact, many countries
have it as a compulsory subject.
Mandatory.
It's something everyone
should do once in their life.
Everyone, no matter how old you are.
But in childhood, with toddlers, it
is a difficult time because they don't have the
tools to move through life.
I have taught boys and girls.
They lack tools.
And there are many shames, it
is a moment when they face the outside world
when they have their own world at home,
more or less comfortable.
Theater allows you, for starters, to
connect with others
in a sincere way.
This is a curious thing
that needs to be clarified.
When you are at school,
you share what
can be shared at school.
But when you do theater,
to begin with,
you have to share the fear, the emotion.
You will work with your emotions,
with your sense of the ridiculous.
Losing the sense of the ridiculous.  We
all try to be as sensible
and correct as possible in life, to
do things more or less well,
not to fall when we walk,
not to stumble, not to do...
Nothing happens, the right to make mistakes,
theatrical teachings
allow you to do this constantly.
In fact, the basis of theater
is the mistake.
You have to make mistakes to learn,
to be able to do it well.
Error, hit, error.
Research how to do it better.
Therefore,
their minds are opened, they lose their fear.  I
remember that, while teaching, there
was a boy who was,
let's say, the bad guy in the group.
There are always roles that go...
There was a dwarf
who was like the most cocky of them all.
The rest were a little afraid of him.
When he made a joke, everyone laughed.
I decided to give him
the most serious character,
the most sensitive,
the one who was the saddest.  He
discovered, within himself,
that not only did this
not make him lose authority
over his peers,
but it showed the rest a side he did
n't know he had
and that made the rest truly
love him
or truly admire him.
He took it very seriously
and began working on it
with great dedication.
With that, he began to
be the leader in a different way,
in a much more honest way,
because he cried,
because he was able to cry
in front of his friends.
And that was like a carom,
that's what happened to the rest.
Well, on that occasion,
I had a problem
with the teachers
because the children wanted to
stop doing all kinds of classes,
all kinds of activities,
because they only wanted to
do theater classes,
and the teachers told me:
“It's becoming a problem
because the parents want them to
study other things.”
In short, it opens up many paths for them,
especially in the mind.
And in their way
of relating to others
and losing their modesty.
Sometimes they say
that actors are the biggest liars.
It is said that an actor lies.  I
think it's the opposite,
we are the people who lie the least.  I
think that citizens in general,
people in general,
build characters for ourselves
that are often not true at all.  We pretend to be
strong when we are fragile, we pretend to be
fragile
when in reality everything is the same for us, we
build a character for ourselves outwardly
and try to be consistent
with this character
throughout our lives.
However, actors live,
precisely, without the mask on,
bringing out from us everything that we
sometimes don't want to see that we have.
This offers children a chance
to see themselves in a different way.
Losing the sense of the ridiculous.
We do a lot of things
or stop doing them
because we are ashamed,
because we are embarrassed.
"I won't be able to do this."  Why not?
There's always a: "Why not?",
and I think that's very healthy.
Then,
on the other hand, when you do theater... I
explained it to them,
and they were very young, right?
We did
Shakespeare's "A Midsummer Night's Dream."
Inevitably, you
start talking about mythology,
talking about Shakespeare
as an author and not just a playwright, you
start talking about his time.
Therefore, they begin to learn
a lot of collateral things
that are related
to general education,
but they see them through them,
through their own bodies.
What Puck represents in the play,
which is a kind of goblin,
has its value
and meaning within the story
and they begin to understand it.
"Where can I learn this?
What books are there about this?"  Their
curiosity is awakened
in an incredible way.
Then they begin to learn that,
without the other, you are nothing,
and that is also important.  It's
not about being the best, it's
about being a strong link
in a strong chain.
A team is formed,
a group is formed
in which everyone helps each other
and rivalries are eliminated.  There
is always someone who says:
“Why do I have fewer sentences?
I want to have more sentences.”  We
all have a protagonist inside.
But, well, when they realize it...
You give them responsibilities
and they realize that they don't have to be
the protagonist in the role.
Because then you have a lot more work
to do behind the scenes too.
You're the one who will help him when he comes out,
you're in charge of the costumes,
you help him...
The feeling of working in collaboration,
all together,
which is the basis of theater,
teaches them a lot.
I'm telling you, I know they
ended up telling me:
"Don't come anymore
because they don't want to do anything else."  And they did it
all.
They made the costumes,
the music, they did everything.  It
was beautiful to see how girls
who didn't dare to say a word
ended up on stage
playing wonderful characters.
This is very nice to see.
There is one aspect
that I think is very important,
which is
learning to speak in public
and know how to convey ideas.  I
don't know if you've ever had
this fear of public speaking.
What would you say to a child or young person
who has this fear?
Speaking in public
is a very special thing.  You
must keep in mind that,
99% of the time,
an actor does not speak
with his own voice,
but through a character.
So, I know what to say, I've
already learned it.  And
I don't say it, she or he says it.
This takes away half of your problem.
For me, public speaking
is what we are doing now.
I'm facing a series of people
who are looking at me
and I don't have a script written, I
don't know what I'm going to say
and I'm the one talking.
This time it's me, not a character.
This has
caused me enormous...
excitement and terrible fear today.
I'm very nervous, I told you.
It is the first thing you have to assume
when you have to speak in public.  It
makes you nervous, who doesn't get nervous?
Because nobody wants to look ridiculous,
that's normal, right?
Nothing really happens,
ridiculousness is a relative thing.
I try...
It's true that we speak
with a text that doesn't belong to us,
but, whether you like it or not,
there are 400 people sitting
like this,
waiting to see what you say.
Anyone who doesn't get nervous about this
is crazy.
You have to be very crazy
for this not to make you nervous.
I think it's a problem, not with the kids,
I think it's also a teacher...
You arrive at class on the first day,
I imagine,
and you see a number of people there, like that.
And you say: “Hello, how are we doing?”  It's
one thing to be in the habit of doing it
and another thing to not be afraid of it.  It's
always scary,
and that's something
I think we need to accept.
When someone has to speak,
if you ever have to:
“Hello, I’m scared.”  Nothing happens.
On the other hand, it's
good to know
that nothing happens if you make a mistake,
nothing happens if you come up empty.
Nobody will die,
nobody will sit there and go “boom!”.
Do you know?  There is no danger, there
is no real risk.
The only risk is your own fear
of looking foolish or ridiculous,
the level you set for yourself,
the bar.
There is something that is sometimes
difficult for us to think about
when we speak in public:
the people who are there
are willing to listen.
In a theater, because they paid.
People don't always pay to listen to you.
Sometimes I think about it
and it makes me very nervous.  They
paid to listen.
Therefore, they also have a provision there.  They
are not a mass of people, they
are individuals,
they are human beings
with a name and surname, each of them.
It's another thing we
often forget.
Public speaking
is speaking to a mass of people.
They are little people with feelings,
with their nerves too.
I imagine that today you
also have something like:
“Well, let's see, I'm here, let's
see what this woman has to tell us.”
You too find yourself in an
uncomfortable situation in your living room.
Therefore, when you think
that the other person is in
almost the same situation as you, you
begin to lose your fear, to relax.  It
is clear that you must know
what you want to explain.
I don't know right now,
because I'm seeing what you're asking me
and I'm building a speech
as I go.
But, well, that's also what life gives you,
the years, the experience
and having a real desire to
share something.
This is another thing
that really takes away your fear,
the idea of: “I want to share
what I have with you.”
You are here to listen
and I am here
to give you everything I have,
and it brings me well-being and pleasure to do so.
Our work, that of actors, does not exist
without you,
the viewer.
A teacher's job,
without students, is meaningless.
Anyone who gives a speech
has an audience, they
have people who are listening to them,
an audience that is there,
waiting for what they will say.  You
will be nervous, you will be scared,
but you are a human being who wants to share
things with other human beings.  There
are teachers here, right?
Are you a teacher?
-I do.
Can you come for a moment, please?
You're used to being in front of people.
-Yes.
-Oh, yes?  And usually...
Let's see, a teacher, sometimes,
those who listen to him are forced to.  It's
not like they're paying to be there.
But, in general, they
are there because they have to be there
and they know they have to and they want to.
There is a difference,
I imagine, tell me if I'm wrong.  It
's very different to see a mass
and glance over it
than to look at them one by one, right?
-Yes, totally.  Try
it, one by one,
and pay attention to a small detail
of each one.
Everyone has their eyes on you.  They
don't look the other way, do they?
-No.
-That's interesting.
-Very much.
-They are waiting for you.
-Well, from you.
-No, now they're looking at you.
-Yes, too.
Now they're looking at you.  They
look at you.
He, the other and she.
You see her moving a foot,
she's a little nervous.
You look at them
and a connection occurs.
-Yes.
When you teach, do you
look at the whole class
or at them individually?
-No, it is looked at individually.
-Oh, yes?
And that makes you lose a little bit of fear.
-And that they are with you more.
-Oh, friend.
This is one of the great challenges
of public speaking:
getting attention.
Capture it.
The only way
to get attention is to give.
Give.
It is an act of generosity.
And this is very noticeable in politicians.  Have
n't you noticed,
when a politician doesn't speak for us?  He
does this, looks inward
and speaks for himself
or for a mass.
When someone looks at you, you
say: “Oh, it’s for me,
he’s talking to me.”
Then, a bond is established
and nerves go... smoke!
-Yes.
-Oh, yes?
-A little.
-Look how beautiful.
Thank you.
-To you.
It's very beautiful
because it's an act of generosity.
Public speaking
is an act of generosity.
"I have something to give you."
From this moment on,
people come with you.
If you don't say something stupid.
Or something out of time.
But in general...
What's more, I've found it,
if you tell people...
In the theater, you can't tell them:
"Hello, I'm really nervous,"
because no one will forgive you, right?
No one will forgive you.
You can't just put them on the program:
"I would have liked to rehearse for 20 more days."  You ca
n't.  But there is something about this,
about communicating, about communication.  We
believe that public speaking
is something for a gentleman or a lady
in front of others who do not exist
or who are a mass.
No, they are individuals, one and the other,
who have their own interests and their own...
If you see someone suddenly doing...
"Oh, I missed one. I'll
try. There's something...".
Of course, speaking
in front of 5,000 people,
I don't know, or 45,000,
but, deep down... I
've talked about it with people from rock,
for example, with musicians,
and it's the same.  They
tell you: “I don't see a shapeless mass
of people singing at the same time,
I want to go to the heart of each one of them.”
Or, at least,
that is the intention.
And that's what makes you
stop thinking about:
"Am I speaking well?
Am I pretty? Can I be understood? Did I
do the right thing by touching my nose?"  You
stop thinking about this
and start communicating with the other person,
breathing
and being just another human being
who has something to share,
nothing more.
It's beautiful, isn't it?
Because if you see it from here, it
takes away some of the fear.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Jorge.
When I was little
, my generation often went to
the cinema, the theatre,
to share
different cultural activities.
My question is:
How can we now,
in the new generations
that come after us,
instill in them a love for art
and so that they can also get involved
in these activities?
Well, look, Jorge, this question worries
me deeply.
Because we are living in
difficult times for lyric poetry.
Because the networks,
because everything has become
much more individualistic,
everything has much more to do with you,
even the opinion of the other
through an artifact,
not even looking you in the eye
and saying "I like" in person,
with a "like" is enough, right?
This worries us very much.
I believe that everything
related to the art world...
Imagine
a world without art.
It's unimaginable.
It's unimaginable!
Imagine if
museums, cinemas,
theaters,
everything related to culture didn't exist.
That regional dances didn't exist,
that cuisine didn't exist, that
none of that existed.
What kind of world would we have?  It
would be the deepest sadness.
Besides, everything
that has to do with art and culture
is directly related
to our social world,
to our history,
to the present, the past and the future.
Art is always the consequence
of a social movement,
of a historical time.
If we deprive children or adolescents
of everything that this gives,
of their references, of their past,
what future will they build?
There are things that are very important.
One must train to be able to have
a job that gives them food,
we must build worlds
where all our needs
are covered,
where everyone has a home
and a fire that gives them warmth.
I understand all of this,
but if we don't offer them
everything that feeds the spirit,
everything that makes us understand the world,
what gives us different points of view
on things,
which is what art
and culture do,
what will they become?
In working machines.
What a bore, right?  What a pain.
I think that...
Sometimes, even forced...
I'm not ashamed of this, I
have a young nephew,
very small, he's not yet a teenager,
and I don't mind forcing him to do this,
the Duke of the Ear if necessary.
Because, later,
when they live certain experiences, they are
never erased from them.
I think it's necessary
for children to forget about their cell phones
and have these types
of experiences you were talking about.
Watching
a movie at home
or on your computer is not the same
as watching it in a cinema,
because they exist for a reason.
Watching a television series is not the same
as watching a play.  It
has nothing to do with it.
Listening to music
on Spotify or with headphones is not the same
as watching a live concert.
Then, when they experience all this,
when you sit them
in front of a painting in the Prado Museum
and they say:
“How long do we have to be here?”.
You say: “Well, we’ll see.”
From this moment on,
you begin to stimulate him.
Because, besides, it's not that difficult.
It's very easy, deep down.
The mind of a child,
of a teenager, is very open, it
is very spongy
for things to enter.
You sit him down in front of "Las meninas"
and tell him to tell you
the story of the dwarf,
which you don't understand.
Let me explain it to you, let me turn
that character into a story.
His imagination starts to run wild
and things start to appear.  I don't
know,
I think it's necessary and mandatory
that culture be big
and accessible to everyone
so that kids
have it as easy as possible.
Because, otherwise,
we are building a society
that doesn't interest me at all:
people with money or not.  And that's
enough.
Either I have money and, therefore, I have a job,
I can have a family and travel,
a car and I don't know what,
or I don't.
This seems very sad to me.
Culture is the food of the spirit.
Of course, you need to have food,
but to exist in happiness
and communion with others
and with the ability to perceive
what is happening around you...
We are becoming increasingly individualistic,
we are very unempathetic.
This is because of being stubborn,
of not looking.  We
believe that things
should be black or white,
and when you get closer to culture,
you realize that nothing is black or white,
but that everything has millions of nuances,
and that helps you understand.
Surely, watching “Las meninas”, he
ends up saying:
“Don't laugh at her, don't call her 'nana'”.
Sure.
I would end up saying it.  I do
n't know, I think we all
have to make an effort.
Because it is something
that is not that difficult to achieve.
And, of course, the politicians.
This is another topic, right?
Because we can all have many interests
and many intentions,
but, well, we have to make it affordable,
of course.
And encourage it.
Hello, Blanca, how are you?  My
name is Luz,
I am the mother of a ten-year-old boy.
As parents, we are concerned about
our children's academic grades,
but we are also very concerned about
transmitting values.
My question is,
from your point of view,
what values do the arts,
in general,
and theater, in particular, transmit?
I think that, above all, pay attention to,
and it's a word
that's been used too much lately:
empathy.  It's
not just about...
Empathy is very special, it
's about putting yourself in the other person's shoes.  It
's not sympathizing with something, it
's not understanding it, it
's putting yourself in the other person's shoes.  I
believe that this is the great value
that this profession
and culture in general transmits.
Anything that happens in life, we
tend to judge it, right?  To
say whether it is good or bad.
You put on the news
and there's some that seems bad to you,
some that seems good to you,
but you almost never
put yourself in that position.  Let's
imagine the most terrible things.  It
's not the same to see a news story
about a hurricane reaching the coast
and say, "Oh my God,"
as to put yourself in that place.
Do the exercise
of putting yourself in that place,
not that of those gentlemen,
but that one in particular,
that mother with that child.
That she is there, on the raft,
with her child in her arms.
Put yourself there.  It would
open our sensitivity
to things much more.
I mean, empathy
is a very hard exercise to do,
but we would be much more tolerant,
much more understanding.
I think this is the great value,
above all else.
My obligation
is to understand a character
and empathize with them,
because otherwise I would never play someone bad.  I would
only make formidable,
wonderful and fantastic characters,
ideal people.
The history of theater,
literature, and art
is full of terrible characters.
And my obligation is to understand them
and empathize with them.
Don't justify them, I insist.
But I do understand them.
This makes you,
to begin with, let your guard down.
Then,
place the responsibilities
not only on one person,
but also understand the world
that has created beings like this.
Because it seems like it doesn't,
but a pastera exists
because we have created a world where it has a place.  It
's no longer just:
"He's a migrant coming to my country,"
but: "How have we built
the world for this to happen,
for this woman
with this child to be here?
How have we built a world
in which there are people
who systematically kill women?
Men who murder women."  It's
not just about saying:
"No, this can't be."
No, wait, why does that happen?
Who is this person?
This would make us understand
what kind of world we are building
and would make us much better people.
We would work to avoid what we
understand to
encourage these types of horrors.
I think this is its great value.
Sometimes children are told:
“This is wrong and that is right.”
And not everything is “right” or “wrong”.
Sometimes, they do things that are wrong
but they don't understand why they do them.  I don't
know, I think it's a job
that allows you, above all, to
put yourself in other people's shoes
and see things with nuances,
not in black and white.
Hi Blanca, my name is Gonzalo Palmeros.
I'm an actor too, I
declare myself addicted to acting.
I'm also from Atlético.
I wanted to congratulate you
on your entire career,
I think it's wonderful, and even
more so today, listening to you speak.
-Wow, that's good.  Thank you very much.
-My question is, well...
As you know and have said before,
a fundamental part of our job
is managing emotions.  I do
n't know if it's ever happened to you
that you've had to go to record,
for example,
as Carlota in "Siete vidas",
and something has happened in your life,
unrelated to your profession,
and you're sad or something.
How did you do it?
How did you get out there, live?  I
don't know, tell us some trick.
Man, it's true that, as much as I say
that acting is my life,
things happen in life
that aren't acting.
Terrible or absolutely wonderful things can happen to you
.
The opposite can also happen,
where you have the happiest day of your life
and you have to say:
"Hello, I'm going to cry for an hour and a half."
This can also happen.  And
I don't feel like it at all
because I'm super happy.  And
I don't think I'll shed any tears.  The
opposite is also true.
You're having a terrible day
and suddenly you have to tell jokes
and be really brilliant.  You
feel like you have grace
somewhere else,
that it has stayed at home.
I think that's why there's no...
You, if you're an actor, will know.  There's
no... There's
no trick to this.
Ultimately, the only advantage you have
is that what you have to do is not you.
I'm not myself when I go on stage.
This may also sound like a
crazy woman, but I'm not.
Well, a little crazy, yes,
but just the right size.  We
all have to have
our little bit of madness,
which is not a bad thing.
I work...
And for me this is real,
the character is not me, it
is a being who has a voice, who has
a word.
A series of things happen to him,
and all he needs is a body,
a voice
and an intelligence to embody it.
It's as if they were ghosts,
let's say, without a body,
and you leave them there.
But what they say is not you.  They
are not your words, they
are theirs.
Therefore, their events
and their emotions are their own.
Then,
it relieves you when you put aside
your mood at that moment.
At that moment.
Then the laughter stops
and you're back to being the same.
Or, hopefully,
you feel much better
because it cleansed you,
because it made you laugh.
Because this has been proven,
when you are very sad, you
just have to laugh a little and...
Moods
don't last forever.  It
is impossible to maintain them.
So,
when something makes you change...
You've heard that funerals
are where the most jokes are told, right?  There
comes a time
when the pain no longer increases, it
can't take any more
and it needs to break.
The same as when you're: "Ha, ha, ha."  You ca
n't be like that for 60 hours
because it would be...
It's impossible, right?
There are times when this change
produces inner well-being.  There
are times when, when you're super happy
and you get to do a tragedy, it
makes you come down a little and say,
"Well, there are still terrible things to
cry about
and pain to suffer."
It's an exercise in willpower,
you know that's how it is.
Deep down,
we are athletes, in a way.  It
sounds strange to say it, but just as
a physical athlete prepares,
warms up, positions his muscles
and starts running,
playing football or pole vaulting,
we do the same.
You do an exercise to cleanse
your spirit, your mind,
and get to work.
You're an athlete
who goes from zero to 100 like that, right?  There is
no more.
But it's always rewarding
because, whatever mood
you're in, you can pour it
into the work of that specific moment.
Whether good or bad, sometimes... They
say that comedy, deep down,
is a succession of immense pains.
What makes us laugh?
A character who is having a terrible time,
everything that happens to him is a disaster.  And
come on, every time he tries, it gets
even worse.
The more the character suffers, the more you laugh.
Deep down, well, there's a bit of...
If you put a bit of tragedy
into comedy,
that's when it's funniest.
hurts more.
This is curious.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Fernando.
I think one of the
most difficult things for an actress
is to do a monologue
because you're there, in front of the audience.
So, I'd like to know
how you manage to learn the text
without losing the thread
and being able
to convey emotion,
without losing the rhythm...
Look, I've only done a monologue
once in my life.
Once.  I'm
not counting what I did
in "The Comedy Club".
Go on stage to do a monologue.
Once in a lifetime and I don't want to repeat it.  I
don't want to repeat it.  I'm
not saying don't do it,
because you can't say no,
lest later
life comes along and surprises you.
But, well, by choice, right from the start,
I don't want to do a monologue again.
I suffered a lot.
This about learning the text, I'm
telling you this so you know,
that's it.
That is, when people say:
“I don't know how you keep all this in your head.”
Well, it's very easy: student.  There's
no intrigue to this, it
's like knowing the tables
or rivers of Spain, it doesn't matter.
Memorizing, that's easy, basically.
It's hours of elbows
rubbing together and studying.
After this sentence comes this one,
then...
And you have your mnemonic rules
to try to sort it out.  There is
no more.
That is, basically,
learning the text, rai.
For me, the hardest thing
is not having anyone by my side.
I live from the perspective of my partner.  That's
why I told you before,
when you speak in public...
I live in the eyes of those who listen to me.
I'm here
because you look at me and because I want to... I
live off of this.
If I don't have a partner
to look up to on stage, I want to die.
So,
this was a shock to me.
The work process is the same
as any play.  You
start by working on the text,
analyzing it, studying it, you
start to see who the character is...
In this case, she played Mary,
the mother of Jesus.
What do you think?
A very mind-blowing text,
the Virgin's monologue
in her last hours of life,
in her last years of life.
The work, in principle,
of analyzing the text is the same:
you create the character, this and that...
The set design, the movements...
Then, you go here, then that...
It was a play in which I had to dialogue
with people who were not on stage,
but I also did their voices.
I said:
“Where do you want to take my son?”  And he
said:
“I’ll take it somewhere I don’t know.”
And he said: “No!”  In other
words, he would do the voice of the other
plus that of this character
and create them on stage,
even if they weren't there.
In other words, it was a job
that would drive you completely crazy.
And, on top of that, he didn't have...
It's a break, a companion always is.
It does half the work for you.  You
just have to look him in the eyes and,
when it's his turn, you give and receive,
and that's it.  I
always say that if I do well
it's because I have excellent colleagues,
that's as clear to me as water.
So, going out on stage alone...
I don't want to go out.  I did
n't want to go out!  I
had a clear outline
of what the movements were like...
Of course you feel like you're going to make mistakes,
much more than when you're doing a normal piece.
Because when you do work with others,
others have their dialogue
and, if you leave,
the other will say theirs, and I'll say: "I'm sorry."
The other person helps you and
, if you don't remember,
the other person does.
If there's no one, me, until the end... I did it for
two years, huh?
Until the last day I had
someone between the boxes just in case.
Sitting in a corner,
just in case I forgot the text.
The man said to me:
"But I've been here for two years
and you've never left."
"Yes, but it gives me peace of mind."
Because all fears multiply.  All.  It's
much scarier.
Not getting to the place,
not keeping up with the rhythm...
You listen to the spectator much more
than when you're with your teammates.
It's a...
Look, I'm sweating just thinking about it.
In other words,
I really enjoyed doing this job,
but I also had a
horribly bad time.  It
only saved me...
I premiered this
in an old deconsecrated chapel,
a church in Barcelona,
and I did it with 250 spectators.
Then, in a theater here in Madrid,
in a room with 180.
I saw them at the same distance
as I see you
and with almost the same light.
Therefore, since I didn't have any
companions on stage, I
had them in the stands.
So, that saved my life, being
able to have...
I was having a dialogue
with each of the spectators.
And I said this sentence
to this person seriously,
and until I saw if he had understood me, I would
n't go to the other person.
This was a place to hold on to,
to save myself from that horror,
because it was a terrible thing.
When the light came on,
and you were there alone, you said:
“Everyone is looking at me!”
And it's horrible, horrible!
When there are more people,
they can look at others,
but if it's just you... You have a
really bad time,
but it's also an experience
that requires
an enormous level of concentration
and a lot of serenity so as not to faint,
so as not to say: "Ugh!".
I have colleagues who have told me
that it's what they like to do the most
because it gives them
absolute freedom for everything.
For me, on the contrary.
I wasn't free from anything there.
In fact, there is another thing
that may seem ridiculous,
but I insist
that I believe that the actor's job
is teamwork.
Without the rest you can't live.
Then,
when a performance ends and you're alone...
You arrive in the dressing room and you're alone, you
have no one to talk to about
how well or badly it went.
You remove your make-up and
go home alone.
It's a terrifying thing.
Terrifying.
Then, I messed around a lot
with lighting, with costumes,
with everyone.
I would finish the show,
I would wait for them to finish
and we would leave together,
because we were a company of six,
even though I was the only one
going on stage,
but we were an important and large company
with whom I would comment.
And this also made the lighting people
or the technical people
devote themselves much more to the show.
I asked them to give me references
of how they had done it every day.
Because you need a reference.
I don't do it well every day.  There
are days when I do it really badly.
Therefore, you need
someone from the outside to tell you...
When you don't have a companion who says:
"What happened to you? I saw you...?".
When you don't have that, you need someone.
Well, that's it, the light booth.
Well, very good, then phenomenal.
So, it's a very particular world,
this monologue thing.
I, the experience of the monologue,
don't know if I want to live it again.
How are you, Blanca?  My
name is Marimar, I'm a composer.
Well, I would like to know,
the day you decided to be an actress,
how you felt.
Then, besides, well, I don't know,
what advice could you give
to people who, apart from that, want to be actresses
or want to dedicate themselves
to the world of art in general?
The day I decided I was going to
dedicate myself to this, I
went to my mother and told her:
“You will never pay me anything again
because I will do something crazy.”
And she understood
and accepted the deal.
In my family, they say I've always
been crazy but responsible.  I
don't know how to eat one thing with the other.  I have
made
seemingly crazy decisions,
but I have always followed them through to the end.
My mother says
that this is a good thing I have,
that when I set a goal,
I go towards it.
Until I see that it doesn't.
If I see that it's not working, I'll give up,
but I'll try until the end.
So, I think that day
was the happiest day of my life.
I panicked, terrified.
Because I didn't know what could happen.
But we never know
what can happen, right?
They say: “Study this career, it
has many opportunities.”
Or not.
Or in the ones that have exits
later you don't find anything
because everyone has said:
"I'll do this one, which has many exits."  Right
?  You
never know what will happen.  There
is a question I always ask myself:
“Why not?”.
It is an important stimulant.
When you suddenly say:
“Look, how lazy,
because I think this is crazy.”
If you say to yourself: “Why not?
Maybe it will work out.”
Okay, there are things
that are riskier than others.
Yes, obviously,
being an actor is a complicated path.
Now more and more, moreover.  There
are shovels of them, a hundred thousand of them come out.
The demand for actors is much lower
than the supply of actors.
But it's a life decision.
I think being consistent
with what you want
is the most difficult thing in the world.
Not everyone decides to do
in life what they want,
but what they believe is convenient.
So, when you take the risk
of wanting something and making it happen,
that's... No matter
how much you fail, you tried.
I knew I might not succeed,
but I would try,
until the end of my days if necessary.
I think this is the big lesson.  It was
given to me by my teacher,
my professor at the
drama school, Pepe Estruch.
That day when I told him:
“I don't want to leave here,
I want to stay at school forever”,
he grabbed me... He
was a very tall, very tall man.  He
took my head,
put it against his chest and said:
“No one will kick you out
of this profession if you hold on.
Hold on.
This is a long-distance race.”
And then I said:
“Come on, the marathon.”  There's nothing
more,
it's the only thing you can say
to a person who likes this.
To me, people who say
they like performing... I don't
trust them either.  It
's not something you have to like, it has to
kill you,
you have to die for it.
Because it bends you from the beginning,
that is, it knocks you down.
If you say, "I like it,"
the first time they tell you no,
that they'll tell you that all the time, you
stop.  It must
be a passion, it
must be an act of faith,
believing in what is not seen,
which does not provide evidence
of its existence, believing in that.
If you don't have this,
the profession will throw you out in two minutes.
Then, my teacher, I remember that,
when we arrived at school...
We had a teacher in first grade.
They took it away from us because it was very big
and this teacher came in.
I felt a huge rejection
because I would have liked to continue
with the first one we had.
That gentleman who replaced her didn't like
me from the beginning.
Rebellious girl, completely silly.
Why not?
He's a new teacher, maybe...
When he arrived, there were
about 20 of us in the class.
He said... He looked at all of us,
as I tell you to look,
one by one, and said:
"But do you really
think that you are actors?
Really?
Think about it for a moment. Do you
really think that you are
and that you will become actors?
Go home, okay?
At most and with a lot of luck, one of the 20.
Surely you are people in the profession,
amateur actors...
Actor or actress? One, with luck.
So, of your own free will,
start leaving."
And I said: "How cruel, the guy!
I really want it!".
He managed to get
35 of us to finish the class.
Not only did we not leave,
we stayed.
Now, I'm also telling you
that there are two of us left from that class.
Working today.
The rest dedicated themselves
to being theater people.
There are set designers, there are
people who write plays,
costumes, there's everything, producers...
But there are only two of us as actors.
The only thing I
can say to anyone who likes this
and wants to be an actor or actress
is to ask themselves
if they are really willing
to sacrifice
everything that needs to be sacrificed.
Many things are left behind.
And endure being told
no 25 times and
yes once.
Endure, ability to endure.
Training, without a doubt.
Study, work, preparation,
respect for your profession,
a lot of respect.
I see little respect
for this profession sometimes
and it makes me very sad.
In fact, even people,
the viewer, the receiver,
sometimes don't know how sacrificial
and hard this profession is.  It
seems like we're partying all day,
having a great time, like
this is happening as if nothing happened.
"A movie? There aren't that many."
No, sorry, I
get up at six in the morning,
I have to shoot at seven, I
put on my eyelashes
from seven in the morning, I
finish at 12 at night, I
get home dead.  You do
n't know what a shoot is,
only those
who have experienced it know.  You
don't know the effort it takes to
put on a theater performance.
It is a very, very sacrificial profession.
Sometimes you only see
the colors, the glamour.
"Look at that dress, it's at this party,
work with that one."
They have had to do many things
to be able to work in certain places.
Endure, love for this profession,
because it is an act of faith.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Araceli.
We really enjoyed
your characters and laughed.
But, in your life specifically,
what role does humor play?
It is fundamental.  I
laugh a lot in life.
Look, I also do characters...
Super serious and all that.  I laugh
a lot.
It's been like this since I was little,
my mother also tells me this,
that she laughed at everything,
even when I was scolded.
I think a sense of humor
is pure life.
Life is so exhausting,
we see so many hard things
happening to us
and to the people around us,
and to the world in general,
that if you don't have a sense of humor
or are unable to smile,
you feel like going
to another planet
or leaving, in general, I don't know.
I think everything has a comedic side.  That's why he
said that great tragedy
always has something of comedy,
and comedies
always have something tragic.
For me, humor is fundamental.
I see everything with a sense of humor.
And that also relaxes me quite a bit,
because also...
My friends call me
"Intensa" Portillo, a nickname
that sometimes I don't know if it's very good.  I
experience everything with great intensity.
The good things, too.
That good thing is fantastic!
That evil is terrible!
And this... I like it.  I
have a friend who says she
's not a "liker", that she's a "coret".
She's not a "like",
she's a "coret".
Well, that's how I am,
very passionate about things.
I think humor
is what makes me relativize,
because otherwise you would
n't take any steps forward.
There are things that leave you very down
and very dusty.
So, laughter is
what allows you to cleanse and sanitize.
Then, because I love to have a good time.
I don't like to cry.  I do
n't know if there are people who love it,
but I, without a doubt, love laughing.
I'm having a good time in life,
I'm very enjoyable.
Yes, sometimes I act stupid.
But, well, I think this is good and healthy.
-Thank you.
-You're welcome.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Ali.
Well, this year I will start my
high school diploma in Performing Arts.
My question is:
What has been the most fun moment
you've had on stage
and what has been the worst?
The most fun thing on stage?
Well, I remember
one that was an anthology.
It's between funny and terrible.  We
were performing at the La Latina theater
a play by Jardiel Poncela
called “Mother: The Father's Drama”.
I played a mother who
had four daughters
who were getting married.
Then, on the wedding day...
It was a delirious comedy.
I am in great danger
because I laugh a lot.
When I laugh on stage, I can't stop.
There are actors
who keep their laughter inside and carry on.
You see their eyes flicker,
but they continue talking.
I am incapable of it.
Once I do “ha”, I
can't stop.
Once I've started, I continue.
Then, in comedies
I have to be super concentrated
because I pee laughing.
It's a big problem.
Plus, I also see my
colleague's work and it makes me laugh.
If he does it well,
then I laugh like a spectator.
Rich.
Well, I was super focused
and, in this scene,
the four brides discovered
that they were sisters of the four grooms
and a mess ensued, okay?
Then, there was a moment
when one of the actors
was coming down some stairs, shouting:
“They're brothers, they're brothers!”.
Forgive me, because I think so... And he
goes down: "They are brothers, brothers!".
He tripped and fell.
Like when you're walking down the street and someone falls...
It's terrible, we laugh.
It's terrible, isn't it?  I
don't know why we laugh,
but it's funny to see someone fall.
Will it be possible?
Well, there, on stage, even more so.  He
fell and then... It
was a laugh too, like dominoes
, bread, bread, bread, in a chain.
One, and the other, the other, the other...
I'm telling you that one of the girls,
who was wearing a wedding dress, was
taken away in a hurry
and was going with the flow, that is...
Literally, she was peeing.
He was pissing himself laughing.
A chain reaction
of “ha, ha, ha, ha, ha” ensued that was
impossible to stop.
On the one hand, we were laughing our heads off
and happy, of course,
because laughter always brings you happiness,
and on the other hand, we were embarrassed...
At that moment,
I was sitting on the floor,
leaning on a table.
I kept getting under the table,
coming out again, hitting it and saying:
“But, let's see!”,
to try to get it to stop,
because there was no way to stop it.
The more I tried to stop it, the worse it got.
Obviously, people noticed.
People aren't stupid and say:
"This isn't the function."  There was
because all the laughter on stage
spread down below.
We were
in that theater in La Latina for about five minutes,
everyone laughing: “Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha”.
Non-stop.
And we no longer knew where we were going.
That was chaos, but wonderful.
When things calmed down a bit,
I stood up and said:
"Forgive us, because it was...
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha. We
'll resume the scene
from a little earlier, let's
see if we can continue."
We had to repeat it, start it again,
and people found it to be
a very fun experience.  It
was explained to other people
who came and said:
"Oh, they told me that they laughed at one
and they didn't laugh at the one I saw."
Word spread that it was a very
funny thing about the show.
I think it's one of the most beautiful moments I've
ever experienced.
Even though we were having a hard time,
people were very committed to it.
This is when I talk about communication
between the audience and the actor.
A beautiful communion is created.  We
were all there together,
in company, and it was very beautiful.
And the worst moment?
I think the worst moments... They
almost never happen to me, huh?
It's to remain blank.
This is the worst!
When suddenly you say... And there's
nothing.
A total void!
You hear: “Crick, crick, crick.”
Because there is nothing!
But not a word, not a sound, nothing!  Phew
!
Like a vertigo.
Then, the time,
which is usually: "One, two...".
The time says: "One...
two...".  That
is, time stretches out, and you say:
“This infinite pause! What do I say now?”.
People who have seen it from the outside have
n't noticed.
Because a white one
usually lasts almost a second.
Unless you're doing a monologue,
there's always someone who...
Either it comes, or the idea comes.
Normally, it goes away the more effort
you make to remember, it's funny.
If you're saying:
"Now comes the sentence of...", it's gone.
Then, I remember one... It
also has its comedic side.
I was doing a Lope de Vega,
“The Bizarries of Belisa”,
and she said to the gallant:
“You are a discreet and understanding gallant,
placid, brave, well-born,
modest, graceful, attentive and well-mannered,
and you only have to speak
to be ungrateful”.
And Blanca Portillo comes out and says:
"You are...".  Phew
!
And it's one thing to forget
a text in a prose work,
but it's another to forget
a few octosyllables...
When you lose the verse,
it's very difficult to improvise.
It is very difficult to improvise in verse.
Then, I said: “You are...
...an ungrateful being.”
Because I only remembered the music.
The rhymes.  I
did that...
But a lot... I will
never forget my friend's face,
which was like: "Huh?".
I think he had his
whole life ahead of him.
And a spectator in the front row...
Excuse me,
but I remember it and I'm dying.  There
were two ladies and one said to the other:
“What did he say?”  I had a
terrible time!
But now I think about it and say:
“Look how cute,
it was true that it was fun.”
But, when a text goes away, it's
horrible.
But I loved this about the lady.
So normal: “What did he say?”
As if it was her problem,
that she didn't understand.
A lot of things can happen to you.
Very many.
Hello, Blanca, how are you?  My
name is Pablo Tercero, I am an actor.  To
tell you that I am very moved to listen to you
and look at you, to
see your eyes, to see your gaze,
how you talk about our profession
and the love we have for it.
That said...
Throughout your career, you have worked
with creative and talented people.
Almodóvar or Milos Forman, for example.
Almost nothing.
So, my question was:
What is the most important thing
or what have you learned from them both?
Then, aside from that...
These people are very talented
and creative, so...
Do you think that this talent
and this creativity
is born with them or is it made?
Thank you.
It's true that I've been very lucky
working with people like that.
I think the best thing you take away from them
is them themselves,
not their jobs.
Get to know them.
In my passion
for relationships with people,
what I actually take away is,
above all, this.
I am lucky to have met
a human being
who also has incredible talent.
When I say this, I
mean a lot of human beings.
And I always stay with the person.
In fact, I do
n't need them to call
me back.
It's a curious thing.
I would like to work with them
and repeat with the people I have
worked with,
who are wonderful, of course they are,
but I have had enough, I am satisfied
to have met them
and to have the opportunity to share.
If they call you back later,
much better.
I think, look,
when I was in school...
In fact, my teacher,
Pepe Estruch,
said that not everyone
has the talent to be an actor.  I have
never believed in talent.
In fact, I was against this
when I was young.
I told him: “Talent doesn't exist,
talent is nonsense.”
And he told me:
"No, we all have a talent. We
have to discover what it's for."
In other words, to be an actor, you
need to have a specific talent.
But we all have one,
the luck is in discovering what it's for.
Talent for what?
One can have talent
for doing a million things.  You
need talent to be a miner.
And not all miners
have the talent to be one.
The interesting thing in life is discovering
what you were made for,
what you were born for.
Or done.
For what?  What is the place
where you could develop what
You get caught up in things
that have nothing to do
with your natural talent.
And this is what my teacher said
produces deep frustration
and even deep pain.
Because you're doing
something that you don't...
He always said
that an actor has to train,
and with training
you can become a good actor.
If you have talent and don't train,
your talent disappears.
If you have talent and you train,
you're the best.
“You can become the reed”, he said.
Since I never believed in this, I
dedicated myself to studying like crazy,
to doing everything that needed to be done.
And he said to me one day:
“You have talent for this.”
And I said to him: “No, no, no, you
already told me about talent...
Talent is something
that I can't touch and that I don't believe in.”
Then, over the years....
Which are already quite a few,
many more than half my life
dedicating myself to this,
and coming across talented people,
very talented,
I realize that it does exist.
There are people who have a gift
for doing what they do.
But you can have a gift
to be the best cook
or to be the best teacher
or to be whatever.
The fortune is that there are those who find it
and unfortunately
there are people who don't.  I
think I wasn't wrong.  I do
n't know if I have talent for this,
but I have seen people suffering
to do something
that didn't cost me much.  And
I never understood it:
“But if this isn’t so difficult.”
"It will be for you."  And you say, well...
Over the years I have realized this,
that I was not wrong
when I chose.
I think that's the trick,
having found from the beginning,
like the one who says,
except being a stewardess,
the thing that,
in a way, you come equipped with as standard.
In a way,
you have a natural disposition
for something.
So, now I do believe in it,
when I meet people who say:
"It's a talent that makes you fall off your ass."  You
also realize that, in 99% of cases,
there is a part of work,
of working hard.
Of studies, of preparation,
of elaboration, of creating teams,
of seeking help... Anyway.
Almodóvar is not just a talent, he
is not magic.  He
has talent, no doubt,
but what he has is love for what he does,
a dedication 24 hours a day,
365 days a year.
So, this talent flies, right?
Now I believe in this,
what my teacher said:
“If you have talent...
If you don't have it,
work hard, put in the effort.
And if you have it, put in the effort too,
because then you will
reach much higher.”
We live in a state where culture
is somewhat set aside,
but I think it
is very important
for the development of a society.
That said,
if you had a Minister of Culture
in this country,
no matter what their political affiliation,
what would you tell them to...?
For...
-I told them a few things, huh?
-Yes, yes, yes, but I don't know.
Thank you.
I feel a deep disappointment
when elections come, there is a campaign
and there is no political leader
who talks about culture.
But systematically.
Not a single one who says:
"Respecting the culture
of our country...".  Nobody.  Nobody
!
Life has also shown me
that Ministers of Culture
almost never have anything to do
with culture.  They
may be people who are dedicated
to some sector of culture, I'm
not saying they aren't,
but the concept, the idea of culture and,
above all, a program,
an idea of what you want to achieve
when you want to do culture.  I have
seen that on many occasions it has
been a ministry to try them out,
see how it goes, and then change them.
People... You
just have to see it too
when you go on tour
and see the theater programmers.
A man who is programming
at a very important theater comes to you
and says: “It's my first year, I
graduated from Libraries...”.
And you say: “How?”.
When they don't tell you:
"I come from the prison system."
"And now you program theater?
What is the criterion?"
I think we are a
very clumsy country with this.  There
is nothing more important
than a cultured country.
What happens
is that a cultured country is scary.
And this has always been linked, we
know that,
just look back.
A cultured country is a country
that chooses and has an opinion,
that has an opinion, that does not let itself be deceived
and that makes demands.
Well, then it's not easy.  We
believe that a good minister
is the one who will lower VAT.
No, no.
A good Minister of Culture
is someone who really cares
that this is something
as important as healthcare... And I
mean it that way.
Like healthcare, like education.
These are basic goods.
That we must worry
about people's access to culture.
Absolute access to culture.
The sponsorship,
of course, of culture
and the people
who dedicate themselves to it.
Why not?
Because we live like bourgeois?
Who said...?
Who was responsible for saying...?
Which Ministers of Culture have
taken it upon themselves to say
that culture is a privileged thing?
If there are millions of things that are
much more subsidized
and much more protected!
Love for this,
creating criteria in people.
What would I tell them?
That they really want to be ministers.
The question would be:
Do you really want to be Minister of Culture?
Why?  To do what?
But let them tell you,
like the Economics guy says:
"I want to raise these taxes to...".
Well, what do you want to do?
"Culture for everyone".
And how is this done?
How much money will you ask for
when you sit
in the Council of Ministers and say:
“How much is there for my department?”
"It's the one that has the least."
"So I'm leaving."
No, let them really fight
for what they want.
and we are still without a patronage law.  I don't
know,
this is really done in other countries
and there are agreements for culture.
There should also be a pact
for healthcare and education
to end the fact that,
every time there is a political change,
everything is destructured.
What takes
three years to build and build,
you can load it up in two months
and it can't be rebuilt.
A pact for culture
and education, which are linked.
Please, so that it is something
that does not depend on
political ups and downs.
But no... There
is no criterion, either.
I don't see the Ciudadanos party fighting
with the I don't know what party over culture
and saying: "No, our position
is much better because of that."
I've never seen them discuss
culture.  Do
you?  Where?
Because I would love to see them.
Have you ever seen a debate about culture
in the Congress of Deputies
?
Not even
from Culture budgets.  I
would ask them this:
Why do they want a Ministry of Culture?
If they don't use it.
Let them take him out!
It's over!
It's a bit desperate.
Quite.  Thank you.
Hello, Blanca, my name is Alfonso.
I'm amazed because you're an actress,
producer, director,
teacher, hostess...
I'd like to know,
of all the things you've learned
in your life,
as well as life lessons,
what would you stick with and why.
I think that, despite all the things I've
done over the years,
I love directing, I love producing,
I think I'm stuck with what we were talking about,
with this magic of this second
of communication with people.
I feel that I am an interpreter
above all else.  Actress.
“Interpreter” is a word
that I love.
I interpret the words
that an author has written.
And with the rules that a director more or less
sets.
I interpret them emotionally,
I convert them, I change the language.
The communication that is established there.
That's why I always say
that I would never know how to choose
between cinema, theatre or television.
But, if I had to choose one, I would never... I would
never exclude theater.  It
would be the only
thing I would never want to give up,
because it produces
this effect that I'm telling you about.  It is
priceless.
Think about it.  Oh, yes?  It
must have happened to you
that you felt an emotion,
you explained it to someone.
And this person has
become emotional with you.
He also shed tears
or laughed.
With this communication, you say:
“This is a friend
to whom I can tell how I feel.”
And this person enters you
with the empathy we were talking about,
puts themselves in your shoes and experiences the same thing.
I have the privilege of living it
every day of my life.
And that's the most beautiful thing
this profession has given me.
Feeling that what I feel is real
and reaches the person on the other side.
We share it.
Communicate.
We lack a lot of communication, it
's a shame.  I'm
telling you the truth.  We do
n't listen, we
don't see, we don't look into each other's eyes.
You're walking down the street
and you don't know who you're going to run into.
I bless
every morning that I walk down the street
and someone smiles when they pass by.
Someone walks past you and smiles at you, and
you say: “Oh!”.
Free of charge, for nothing, because yes.
You see someone looking bad
and you feel like saying:
“Is something wrong with them?”  And
we don't.
I have the privilege of communicating
every day of my life.
This is the cane.
Much more than putting on a show
and earning a good salary.
Much more important.
Well, anyway, looking into your eyes, I
thank you
because it has been really nice to
be here with you.
Thank you for each of the questions
and for sharing this madness of mine.  I
truly invite
each of you,
if you have the opportunity,
to touch it, to
touch this world in some way,
to get closer to it.
I hope to see you
in theaters around the world.  I'll
wait for you, okay?
Thank you.